Guide to the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service records ARC.129
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service records
1866-1989
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service
Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service
Brooklyn Bureau of Charities
Sheltering Arms Nursery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Bureau of Social Services and Children's Aid Society
Brooklyn Children's Aid Society
ARC.129
66.25 Linear Feet in forty-two boxes, thirty three film canisters, nine wrapped scrapbooks, and one slide binder
The collection contains the records of the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service and its predecessor organizations, including the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service Service and Children's Aid Society, the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities, the Brooklyn Childen's Aid Society, and the Sheltering Arms Nursery. The collection comprises sixty five linear feet, includes various types of records (administrative records, housing ledgers, scrapbooks, photographs, audiovisual media, etc.), and spans the years 1866 to 1989. The Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service was a charitable organization with a focus on aiding the impoverished, children, and people with disabilities. The Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service was renamed Brooklyn Community Services in 2010 and continues to operate today.
Historic chronology
Chronology
1866
Brooklyn Children's Aid Society founded.
1866
Union of Christian Work founded.
1870
Sheltering Arms Nursery founded.
1878
Brooklyn Bureau of Charities founded.
1901
Union of Christian Work consolidated with the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities.
1920
Sheltering Arms Nursery absorbed by the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society.
1945
Brooklyn Bureau of Charities renamed Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service.
1948
Brooklyn Bureau of Social Services and Brooklyn Children's Aid Society merge, becoming the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Services and Children's Aid Society.
1969
Brooklyn Bureau of Social Services and Children's Aid Society renamed Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service.
2010
Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service renamed Brooklyn Community Services.
Sources:
Goldman, Esther. 100 Years of Concern for Human Needs, 1866-1966. Brooklyn, N.Y.: Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service and Children's Aid Society, 1966.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accessions 1991.002 and V1991.110 were gifts of Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service, 1991.
Related Materials
Related archival collections held by BHS include:
Alfred T. White Tower and Home and Riverside Apartment Buildings records (1978.154)
The Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn records (1985.093)
Brooklyn charitable organizations for the poor collection (1985.104)
Brooklyn charitable organizations for the aged publications (1985.105)
Brooklyn charitable organizations for children publications (1985.106)
Brooklyn charitable organizations for people with disabilities collection (1985.108)
Brooklyn charitable organizations for working women collection (1985.109)
Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection (ARC.141)
Brooklyn Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor annual reports and publications (ARC.179)
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains the records of the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service and its predecessor organizations, including the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service Service and Children's Aid Society, the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities, the Brooklyn Childen's Aid Society, and the Sheltering Arms Nursery. The collection comprises sixty five linear feet, includes various types of records (administrative records, housing ledgers, scrapbooks, photographs, audiovisual media, etc.), and spans the years 1866 to 1989.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
Series 1: Brooklyn Bureau of Charities and Bureau of Community Service records
Series 2: Brooklyn Children's Aid Society records
Series 3: Sheltering Arms Nursery records
Series 4: Photographs
The first series contains the records of the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service, the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service and the Children's Aid Society (after the 1948 merger), the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service (pre-merger), and the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities.
The second series contains the records of the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society prior to its merger with the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service in 1948.
The third series contains records of the Sheltering Arms Nursery prior to its acquisition by the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society in 1920.
The fourth series contains photographs from all organizations.
Other Finding Aids
A detailed survey of the records comprising accession 1991.002 (the bulk of this collection) is available in the 1991.002 accession file. Additionally, an inventory of the collection's films is available in the collection's electronic accession file. Please consult library staff for more information.
Custodial History
Prior to acquisition by BHS, the records comprising accession 1991.002 (the bulk of this collection) were surveyed by Anne E. Bowler.
Historical note
The Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service was a charitable organization with roots that date back to the 19th century. Its predecessor organizations included the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society (established 1866), the Union of Christian Work (established 1866), the Sheltering Arms Nursery (established 1870), and the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities (established 1878). Over the years these organizations consolidated, culminating in the merger of the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service and the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society in 1948. The organization was renamed the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service in 1969, and then rebranded as Brooklyn Community Services in 2010. The mission of these organizations generally remained the same, with a focus on aiding the impoverished, children, and people with disabilities.
Annual reports; Publications; Photograph albums; Photographs; Clippings (information artifacts); Administrative records; Registers (lists); Pamphlets; Family social work -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children |x Institutional care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; People with disabilities |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blind |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Correspondence; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Abused children |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Minutes; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child welfare -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Scrapbooks; Charities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Poor |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Juvenile delinquency |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Child health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social work with older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Reports; Lantern slides; Color slides; Audiotapes; Motion pictures (visual works); Nursing homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Social case work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Foster care -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Rockland County (N.Y.); Far Rockaway (New York, N.Y.); Periodicals; Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service; White, Alfred Tredway; Riley, Thomas J.; Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service; Brooklyn Children's Aid Society; Brooklyn Bureau of Social Services and Children's Aid Society; Draper, Mary Childs; Brooklyn Bureau of Charities; Sheltering Arms Nursery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Peddy, Lester; Ely, Paul F.
- Series 1: Brooklyn Bureau of Charities and Bureau of Community Service records, 1881-1989; 3518
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains the records of the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service (BBCS) and its predecessors, the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities and the Bureau of Social Service and Children's Aid Society, dating from 1881 to 1989. It includes reports, publications, Board of Directors and executives' papers, committee files, scrapbooks, and audiovisual media. Photographs related to the BBCS and its predecessor organizations can be found in Series 4: Photographs.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into ten sub-series:
  Sub-series 1.1: Reports and publications
  Sub-series 1.2: Board of Directors records
  Sub-series 1.3: Courts Committee
  Sub-series 1.4: Tenement House Committee and Housing Committee
  Sub-series 1.5: Committee on the Blind and related events
  Sub-series 1.6: Women's Committee
  Sub-series 1.7: Papers of individuals
  Sub-series 1.8: Audiovisual media
  Sub-series 1.9: Scrapbooks
  Sub-series 1.10: Miscellaneous
  - Sub-series 1.1: Reports and publications, 1881-1989; 66428; 5.25 Linear Feet in eleven boxes
    Arranged alphabetically, with miscellaneous publications placed at the end of the sub-series.
    The sub-series contains annual reports, annual meeting reports and programs, by-laws, newsletters, and other publications, dating from 1881 to 1989.
    - Annual Meeting reports and programs, 1903-1966; 66685 (Box 13)
    - Annual Report, 1881; 66430 (Box 27)
    - Annual Report (bound volumes), 1882-1926; 66727 (Box 31)
    - Annual Reports, 1885-1925; 66523 (Box 11)
    - Annual Reports, 1926-1969; 66524 (Box 12)
    - Annual Reports, 1970-1989; 66673 (Box 13)
    - Bi-weekly reports, 1964-1967; 66435 (Box 9)
    - The Bureau Chat (two issues), 1941-1945; 66392 (Box 7)
    - Brooklyn Association for Improving Conditions of the Poor publications, 1933, 1943-1954; 66680 (Box 13)
    - Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association: A Report of Services Rendered Through Christmas Seals, 1938; 66681 (Box 13)
    - Fifty and One Hundred Year Anniversary books, 1916, 1966; 66707 (Box 13)
    - The Friendly Light Magazine (twenty four issues), 1930-1966; 66394 (Box 7)
    - The Full Circle: A Newsletter By and For Foster Parents and Children at the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service (six issues), 1971-1975; 66400 (Box 7)
    - Harriman Farm School promotional books with photographs, circa 1955; 66712 (Box 24)
    - The House Organ (five issues), 1914-1915; 66396 (Box 7)
    - Long-Term Homemaker Service: Project Report, 1958; 66682 (Box 13)
    - The Open Door, 1927-1932; 66405 (Box 7)
    - The Open Door, 1940-1978; 66485 (Box 8)
    - The Shelter Island Scoop (five issues), circa 1978-1982; 66407 (Box 8)
    - Assorted reports, by-laws, publications, and cookbooks, 1916-1971; 66686 (Box 16)
    - Assorted pamphlets, 1909-1970s; 66687 (Box 17)
  - Sub-series 1.2: Board of Directors records, 1899-1974; 66329; 1.5 Linear Feet in three boxes
    The sub-series contains Board of Directors and Executive Committee meeting minutes (1899-1907 and 1960-1974) and Fiscal Review Committee files (1973-1974).
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Board of Directors and Executive Committee meeting minutes ledger, 1899-1907; 66705 (Box 24)
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1960-1968; 66327 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1968-1974; 66328 (Box 2)
    - Fiscal Review Committee, 1973-1974; 66701 (Box 2)
  - Sub-series 1.3: Courts Committee, 1907-1959; 66333; 2 Linear Feet in four boxes
    Arranged alphabetically, with miscellaneous files placed at the end of the sub-series.
    The sub-series contains records relating to the Courts Committee, dating from 1907 to 1959. It includes reports, minutes, correspondence, and other files.
    - Annual reports and minutes, 1913-1914; 66334 (Box 2)
    - Annual reports and minutes, 1935-1943; 66335 (Box 2)
    - Adolescents' Court, 1931-1934; 66336 (Box 2)
    - Adolescents' Court, 1936; 66337 (Box 2)
    - Adolescents' Court, 1937; 66338 (Box 2)
    - Adolescents' Court, 1940-1949; 66339 (Box 2)
    - Adolescents' Court, 1952-1957; 66340 (Box 2)
    - Bloede Estate, 1913-1914; 66341 (Box 2)
    - Brennan Bill (disorderly conduct), 1913-1914; 66342 (Box 3)
    - Brooklyn Civic Club, 1915; 66343 (Box 3)
    - Buildings Committee, 1912-1915; 66344 (Box 3)
    - Case Reports, 1913-1915; 66345 (Box 3)
    - Children's Court, 1912-1915; 66346 (Box 3)
    - Domestic Relations Court, 1907-1915; 66347 (Box 4)
    - Family Court, 1956-1959; 66348 (Box 4)
    - Finger Print Bureau, 1913-1915; 66349 (Box 4)
    - Judicial Statistics Committee, 1910-1914; 66350 (Box 4)
    - Magistrates Court, 1912-1915; 66351 (Box 4)
    - Monday Club, 1908-1914; 66352 (Box 4)
    - Probation Committee, 1912-1915, 1932; 66353 (Box 5)
    - Prostitution, 1910-1915; 66354 (Box 5)
    - Reports, 1926; 66706 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous subjects, 1913-1915; 66355 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1912-1915; 66356 (Box 5)
  - Sub-series 1.4: Tenement House Committee and Housing Committee, 1911-1940; 66359; 4 Linear Feet in five boxes
    The sub-series contains files relating to the Tenement Housing Committee and the Housing Committee, dating from 1911 to 1940. It includes annual reports, committee reports, and clippings and correspondence belonging to Housing Committee Secretary Joseph Fink.
    - Tenement House Committee annual reports, 1911-1916; 66675 (Box 13)
    - Committee reports, 1926-1929; 66361 (Box 5)
    - Committee reports, 1930-1931; 66362 (Box 6)
    - Multiple Dwellings Bill, 1912, 1927-1937; 66364 (Box 6)
    - The Multiple Dwelling Law, 1931; 66716 (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous papers and correspondence, 1920-1930; 66368 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink articles: Fire escapes, 1927-1928; 66370 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink articles: Housing legislation, 1924-1927; 66372 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink articles: Model tenements, 1927-1929; 66374 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink articles: Pushcarts, 1928-1929; 66376 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink correspondence and papers: Fire, 1916-1936; 66377 (Box 6)
    - Joseph Fink newspaper clippings: Fire, 1921-1937; 66379 (Box 7)
    - Joseph Fink newspaper clippings: Boston housing, 1940; 66381 (Box 7)
    - Joseph Fink newspaper clippings: Prohibition, 1931; 66382 (Box 7)
    - Joseph Fink newspaper clippings: Miscellaneous, 1930-1931; 66384 (Box 7)
  - Sub-series 1.5: Committee on the Blind and related events, 1913-1987; 66676; 3.5 Linear Feet in six boxes
    The sub-series contains records relating to the Committee on the Blind and events such as the Week for the Blind and the Day for the Blind, dating from 1913 to 1987. It is primarily composed of event programs, but also includes annual reports and a photograph album/scrapbook. Additional photographs documenting the organizations work with the blind can be found in Series 4: Photographs.
    - Committee on the Blind annual reports, 1913-1914, 1921-1922; 66684 (Box 13)
    - Blind Women of Brooklyn - The Happy Days Review programs, 1935; 66709 (Box 14)
    - Eleventh Annual Card Party for the Benefit of the Blind and Handicapped, 1940; 66708 (Box 14)
    - Week for the Blind annual programs, 1929-1947; 66678 (Box 14)
    - Week for the Blind annual programs, 1948-1956; 66679 (Box 15)
    - Week and Day for the Blind annual programs, 1957-1970; 66710 (Box 25)
    - Day for the Blind annual programs, 1971-1978, 1980, 1987; 66711 (Box 26)
    - Brooklyn Week for the Blind photograph album and scrapbook (o), 1957; 66695 (Box 21)
  - Sub-series 1.6: Women's Committee, 1969-1985; 66755; 1.35 Linear Feet in two folders and one scrapbook
    The sub-series contains a Women's Committe publicity scrapbook (1969-1980) and meeting agendas and minutes (1974-1985).
    - Women's Committee publicity scrapbook (m), 1969-1980; 66699 (Box 22)
    - Women's Committee meeting agendas and minutes (two folders), 1974-1985; 66756 (Box 35)
  - Sub-series 1.7: Papers of individuals, 1908-1967; 66411; 0.5 Linear Feet in one box
    Arranged alphabetically by surname.
    The sub-series contains papers belonging to five leaders of the Bureau and its predecessor organizations, dating from 1908 to 1967.
    Mary Childs Draper was President of the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities and later the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service and Children's Aid Society. These papers include speeches and memoranda dating from 1942 to 1951.
    Paul F. Ely served as the Bureau's Secretary, Director, and President. His papers include a photographic portrait, resume, clipping, and ephemera relating to the Brooklyn Savings Bank (of which he was President), dating from 1960 to 1963.
    Lester Peddy was Executive Director of the Bureau. His papers consists of correspondence, memoranda, and reports that were sent between Peddy and Ely between 1961 and 1967.
    Thomas J. Riley served as General Secretary of the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities. His papers include Reports of the General Secretary and a typescript titled "History -- Finances -- and Administration of the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities 1878-1926." The papers date from 1908 to 1926.
    Alfred T. White was a founder of both the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society (where he served as Vice President) and the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities (where he served as Secretary and then President for over twenty nine years). His papers include a speech, biographical writings, correspondence, and a scrapbook documenting his time as President of the Bureau and commemorating his life, dating from 1920 to 1921.
    - Mary Childs Draper, 1942-1951; 66420 (Box 8)
    - Paul F. Ely, 1960-1963; 66422 (Box 8)
    - Lester Peddy, 1961-1967; 66423 (Box 8)
    - Thomas J. Riley, 1908-1926; 66425 (Box 8)
    - Alfred T. White, 1920-1921; 66426 (Box 9)
  - Sub-series 1.8: Audiovisual media, 1960s-1973; 66714; 34.25 Linear Feet in two boxes and thirty three film canisters
    Other Finding Aids
    An inventory of the films is available in the collection's electronic accession file. Please consult library staff for more information.
    The sub-series contains audiovisual media related to Bureau, specifically thirty six 35 mm film reels, two 16 mm film reels, and two magnetic audio tapes. The bulk of the sub-series consists of the film "Some People from Brooklyn" (1965). Due to the large amount of film, it is assumed that it includes b-roll in addition to the edited motion picture. The sub-series also includes two 16 mm films labeled "Brooklyn Bureau of Community Services 'Updated Version'" (circa 1960s) and one audio recording of a WNYC radio program titled "Homes--Not Hospitals" (1973).
    - Brooklyn Bureau of Community Services "Updated Version" 16 mm motion picture reels (two reels), circa 1960s; 66730 (Reel loose cans)
    - "Some People from Brooklyn" magnetic audio tape, 1965; 66717 (Box 28)
    - "Some People from Brooklyn" 35 mm motion picture reels (thirty one reels), 1965; 66728 (Reel loose cans)
    - "Some People from Brooklyn" 35 mm motion picture reels (five reels), 1965; 66729 (Box 32)
    - "Homes -- Not Hospitals" WNYC program magnetic audio tape, 1973; 66718 (Box 28)
  - Sub-series 1.9: Scrapbooks, 1922-1983; 66688; 8.75 Linear Feet in ten scrapbooks
    The sub-series contains scrapbooks that primarily contain publicity clippings, dating from 1922-1983.
    - Scrapbooks (a and b), 1922-1925; 66689 (Box 18)
    - Scrapbooks (c, d, and e), 1930, 1938-1941; 66690 (Box 19)
    - Scrapbook (f), 1941-1943; 66691 (Box 20)
    - Unbound scrapbook pages (g), 1943-1945; 66692 (Box 20)
    - Barbara Ann Smith scrapbook (h), 1947; 66693 (Box 21)
    - Unbound scrapbook pages (i), 1947-1950; 66696 (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook (j), 1950-1958; 66697 (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook (k), 1965-1968; 66694 (Box 21)
    - Scrapbook (l), 1976-1983; 66698 (Box 22)
    - Scrapbook (n), 1977-1981; 66700 (Box 23)
  - Sub-series 1.10: Miscellaneous, 1887-1974; 66445; 1.4 Linear Feet in five boxes
    The sub-series contains a variety of records that did not fit into the other sub-series, including a copy of the Bureau's Certificate of Incorporation, one financial ledger (1920s), files relating to the merger of the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society with the Bureau of Social Service, reports of the District Nursing Committee, and assorted other files dating from 1887 to 1974.
    - Certificate of Incorporation (copy), 1887; 66447 (Box 9)
    - Change of Name, 1944-1952; 66451 (Box 9)
    - Children's Aid Society: Arthur Nash Affair, 1950; 66331 (Box 2)
    - Children's Aid Society: Miscellaneous papers and correspondence, 1947-1960; 66332 (Box 2)
    - District Nursing Committee reports, 1910-1919; 66761 (Box 31)
      General
      See also The Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn records, 1985.093 (the successor to the District Nursing Committee).
    - Financial ledger, 1920s; 66757 (Box 35)
    - Letterhead, circa 1970s; 66759 (Box 9)
    - Merger, 1947-1949; 66452 (Box 9)
    - New Building, 1927; 66453 (Box 9)
    - Public Relief, 1913-1915; 66456 (Box 9)
    - Public Relief, 1913-1915; 66492 (Box 10)
    - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1903; 66495 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous papers and correspondence, 1879-1913; 66462 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous papers and correspondence, 1915-1974; 66465 (Box 10)
- Series 2: Brooklyn Children's Aid Society records, 1866-1956; 3516; 5 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and three oversize boxes.
  This series contains records of the Brooklyn Children's Aid Society, including annual reports (1872-1946), one certificate of incorporation, a scrapbook and photograph album, two publications titled Summer Relief for Little Children and Thirty-Five Years of Saving Services, and six registers documenting the disposition of children being sheltered by the Society.
  The registers generally list the name of child admitted; case, city, and state numbers; dates the children were admitted, committed, expiration, and discharged; who the children were committed by (public agency or relatives); date of birth of the child and age of the child when committed; if the children were committed or non-committed to boarding homes, Herriman Farm School, or the Wavecrest facilities (Far Rockaway); remarks; and temporary home.
  Photographs related to the organization can be found in Series 4: Photographs.
  Sub-series 1.10: Miscellaneous contains files related to the Society's merger with the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities.
  - Certificate of Incorporation (copy) and Purposes of the Children's Aid Society, 1866; 66442 (Box 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1872-1905; 66733 (Box 33)
  - Annual Reports, 1907-1946; 66734 (Box 34)
  - Annual Reports, 1907-1941; 66674 (Box 13)
  - Thirty-Five Years of Life Saving Service 1876-1911, 66735 (Box 34)
  - Summer Relief Work for Little Children, 1912-1921; 66736 (Box 34)
  - Temporary shelter admissions ledger, 1918-1929; 66715 (Box 27)
  - Brooklyn Children's Aid Society scrapbook (V1991.110.302), circa 1922; 66720 (Box Prints by Accession OS13)
  - Admission ledger vol. III, 1923-1930; 66758 (Box 35)
    Loose pages have been sleeved and foldered for preservation purposes.
  - Transfer book, 1931-1933; 66724 (Box 30)
  - Temporary Home record, 1933-1939; 66723 (Box 30)
  - Child Day Register, 1939-1944 (Box 41)
  - Child Day register, 1945-1946; 66721 (Box 29)
  - Child Day Register, 1947 (Box 42)
  - Child Day register, 1948-1956; 66722 (Box 30)
- Series 3: Sheltering Arms Nursery records, 1871-1917; 3517; 2.7 Linear Feet in five boxes
  The Sheltering Arms Nursery (SAN) records include annual reports, admissions ledgers, and an event program, dating from 1871 to 1917. The ledgers log information about each child admitted to SAN and include the following categories: age of child, religious affiliation, health status upon arrival, family information such as the reason the child was admitted, ethnic heritage, and the date and reason the child was discharged from SAN.
  - Index of names belonging to ledger, 1873-1919; 66460 (Box 10)
  - Admissions ledger, 1871-1890; 66702 (Box 24)
  - Admissions ledger, 1873-1891; 66703 (Box 24)
  - Admissions ledger, 1891-1914 (Box 29)
  - Admissions ledger, 1906-1917; 66704 (Box 24)
  - Admissions ledger, 1914-1917 (Box 40)